Guide to the Henry Margenau Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Henry Margenau papers
1927-1990
MS 129
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3.5
(8 boxes)
The papers document Henry Margenau's professional career as a physicist and philosopher of science. They chiefly consist of correspondence and published and unpublished writings.
Margenau, Henry, 1901-1997
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Henry Margenau, 1977 and 1994, and transferred from the Kline Science Library, 1977.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in two series: Series I. Personal and Correspondence, 1931-1989. Series II. Writings, 1927-1990.
Scope and Contents
The Henry Margenau Papers are arranged in two series: Personal and Correspondence, and Writings. The collection reveals very little about Margenau's personal life, but it does afford the researcher a good picture of his personality. Through his philosophical and ethical writings and speeches, the researcher can study the workings and development of Margenau's philosophy and thought. Specifically, the researcher can trace his evolution from a specialist in spectral line broadening to a philosopher of science, religion, ethics, and the power of the human mind. Margenau's correspondence and publications reveal not only the great diversity of thought within the scientific community, but also that the establishment of scientific "truth" is a long and complex process. For example, the collection documents the disagreement and tension surrounding the acceptance of such theories as relativity and quantum mechanics, as well as the serious attention prominent scientists paid to notions like extrasensory perception and parapsychology. Margenau's papers also reveal the connection between science, government, and industry. Rather than work solely within the walls of a university, Margenau's prominence at Yale led him to consult for the Argonne National Laboratories, General Electric, and the Lockheed Corporation, among others, and he was long affiliated with the Office of Naval Research.
There are biographical musings made by Margenau in June 1963 on five Soundscriber discs in Historical Sound Recordings (HSR) in the Yale University Library. The researcher must make an appointment with the HSR curator in order to listen to the discs.
Biographical / Historical
Henry Margenau was born on April 30, 1901 in Bielefeld, Germany. Largely self-taught and ambitious, Margenau was trained to be an elementary school teacher. In 1922, however, he emigrated from Germany, settled in Nebraska with a distant relative, and worked as a farm hand. He attended Midland Lutheran College from 1923 to 1924, majored in Latin, and completed his degree in one year. He came to physics quite by accident, when he accepted an assistantship to Dr. Moore, a research physicist at the University of Nebraska, in the summer of 1924. In addition to assisting Dr. Moore, Margenau took courses in physics and mathematics, and in the fall of 1925, began taking graduate level courses. By the spring of 1926, he had a master of science degree in physics. His benefactor and mentor died, but Margenau was retained by the university to continue doing research and to work as an instructor.
Margenau's master's thesis on the Zeeman Effect was published, and he was offered a fellowship from the Yale University physics department in 1927. After two years at Yale, Margenau had completed his Ph.D. in physics. He then went to study quantum theory in Europe on a Sterling Fellowship and returned to Yale in the fall of 1931, with the promise of an assistant professorship after an additional year as an instructor. He was assistant professor of physics from 1931 to 1939, at which time he was made an associate professor.
During World War II, Margenau stayed at Yale and continued to teach. With the arrival, in 1941, of Ernst Cassirer, a prominent philosopher and physicist, Margenau's interests shifted to philosophy. Cassirer and Margenau co-taught a graduate course on Kant and Neo-Kantianism, and in 1944 collaborated on an English edition of Determinismus and Indeterminismus in Der Modern Physik. Unfortunately, Cassirer died before the completion of the project, and Margenau did not continue the work in his absence. Rather than augment and amplify the text as had been planned, Margenau left it as it was, and added a preface over his name as well as a new bibliography. The book was eventually published in 1956.
In 1945 Margenau was promoted to full professor and, in 1950, he received the first joint appointment in physics and philosophy to be offered by Yale, the Eugene Higgins Professorship of Physics and Natural Philosophy. Margenau retired Emeritus from Yale in 1969, but continued to research and write about physical phenomena as well as philosophy and ethics. In the 1960s he developed a considerable interest in the problems of parapsychology, psychical research, and the physical reality of consciousness. Einstein's Space and Van Gogh's Sky (1982), for example, a book Margenau wrote with psychologist Lawrence LeShan, is an exploration of psychic phenomena and perception.
Though Margenau was affiliated with Yale from the 1920s onward, his reputation and professional activities took him all over the world and to many institutions. In 1939 he received a fellowship from the Institute of Advanced Study at Princeton, where he worked with Eugene Wigner and Archibald Wheeler. He was visiting professor at the University of California in 1947, and at the University of Heidelberg in 1953 and 1971. He was at Carleton College in 1953-1954, and at the University of Tokyo under the auspices of a Fulbright Lectureship in 1960. He taught at Whitman College in 1971-1972, and was a Hadley Fellow at Bennington College in 1975. He was a Joseph Henry Lecturer in 1954, and a National Phi Beta Kappa lecturer in 1965. Margenau's professional memberships included the American Physics Society, the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, the American Association for the Advancement of Science, and the Académie Internationale de Philosophie des Sciences in Brussels. He was president of the Philosophy of Science Association and the New England section of the American Physics Society. Margenau served as vice president of the Connecticut Academy of Science and was a member of Phi Beta Kappa and Sigma Xi.
Henry Margenau has been referred to as the most important philosopher of physics of his generation and one of the most eminent philosophers of science in the twentieth century. He was the recipient of a number of honors and awards, including the San Marcos University Medal in 1951, the Century Award from Michigan State University in 1955, and the Devane Medal in 1969. He was in great demand as a consultant and worked in that capacity for MIT's Radiation Laboratory, the Atomic Energy Commission, the National Bureau of Standards, Argonne National Laboratories, General Electric, and the Lockheed Corporation. The latter, for example, had been assigned by the Air Force to study the physical processes taking place in the fireball created by exploding the first hydrogen bomb. Margenau's early work on spectral line measurement led Lockheed to seek his expertise; measuring the spectral lines produced by the bomb's explosion was the key to discerning the bomb's internal heat, and necessary for the success of the project.
Margenau was a prolific author. His books include: Physics: Principles and Applications (1949), The Nature of Concepts (1950), Open Vistas (1961), Ethics and Science (1964), Scientific Indeterminism and Human Freedom (1968), The Scientist (1965), Integrative Principles of Modern Thought (1972), and The Miracle of Existence (1984). He coauthored Foundations of Physics (1936), with R. Bruce Lindsay; The Mathematics of Physics and Chemistry (1943), with George Murphy; Theory of Intermolecular Forces (1969, 1971), with N. Kestner; and co-edited Cosmos, Bios, Theos (1992), with Roy Abraham Varghese. Margenau also published numerous physics and philosophical articles, and served as editor of such journals as Foundations of Physics, Main Currents in Modern Thought, Journal of the Philosophy of Science, American Journal of Science, Reviews of Modern Physics, Journal of Chemistry and Physics, Journal of Quantitative Spectroscopy and Radiative Transfer. He was consulting editor for the Time Life Science Series.
Henry Margenau became a citizen of the United States in 1930, and married Louise M. Noe in 1932. They have three children: Rolf Carl, Annemarie Luise, and Henry Frederick.
Nuclear physics; Philosophy; Physics; Quantum theory; Philosophers; Physicists; Brattain, Walter H. (Walter Houser), 1902-1987; Eccles, John C. (John Carew), 1903-1997; Einstein, Albert, 1879-1955; Margenau, Henry, 1901-1997; United States. Office of Naval Research
- Personal and Correspondence, 1931-1989; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The first folder in this series, "Personal," includes Margenau's personal creed, notes, biographical newspaper clippings, and reviews of Vistas in Physical Reality (1976), a festschrift celebrating Margenau's career. The correspondence in the series is arranged alphabetically by last name of the correspondent and includes both incoming and outgoing letters. Much of the correspondence consists of travel arrangements, academic recommendations, and thank you notes. A large portion of the series pertains to Margenau's retirement in May, 1969. Yale celebrated the event with a symposium in Margenau's honor, and he received numerous letters of congratulation. Although Margenau maintained contact with many physicists, philosophers, psychologists, and parapsychologists, the volume of correspondence with them is rather slight. There are, however, quite interesting letters that deal with major questions in the field of physics. Margenau, for example, discusses probability theory with Walter Brattain, parapsychology with Gardner Murphy, and the Einstein-Podolski-Rosen Paradox with Nick Fremont-Smith. The letters tend to be brief, and center primarily around articles and published responses to them. Despite the routine nature of many of the letters in the series, as a whole it provides broad insight into Margenau's philosophy and interactions within and outside of the scientific community.
  - Personal, 1948-1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence
    - A-C, 1931-1983 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Benor, Daniel [includes three papers by Sir John C. Eccles], 1982 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - D-E [includes letter from Albert Einstein in German], 1936-1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - F-H [includes equation by Enrico Fermi], 1955-1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - J-L, 1940-1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Keppel, John, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
    - M-O, 1956-1983 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - P-R, 1955-1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - S-U, 1959-1969 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - V-Z, 1932-1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Unidentified surnames, 1969-1986 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Writings, 1927-1990; Series II
  This series is comprised of five sections: articles; books; discussions; speeches, lectures, symposia; and other. Each section is arranged alphabetically by title, and, unless otherwise specified, contains materials that were written by Henry Margenau. The first folder in the series contains a list of Margenau's publications, but it is undated and not all inclusive.
  The first folder in the articles section (1929-1980) contains several book reviews written by Margenau. The remainder of the section is divided into Margenau's philosophical and scientific articles. The philosophical articles cover Margenau's views on physics and its role in the world, and his personal ethical and religious thoughts and concerns. They also include some musings on parapsychology and extra sensory perception. The scientific articles are highly technical essays in various fields of physics. They include useful information on who funded Margenau's research, the purposes behind it, and the uses to which it was put. They therefore provide context for the researcher who might lack a specialized knowledge of physics.
  The books section (1943-1985) primarily consists of correspondence, reviews, drafts, and notes regarding a selection of Henry Margenau's books. They include: Einstein's Space and Van Gogh's Sky (1982), Ethics and Science (1964), The Mathematics of Physics and Chemistry (1943), The Miracle of Existence (1984), Open Vistas (1961), Physics and Philosophy (1978), one chapter from an unidentified book, and one chapter from Measurement in Quantum Mechanics, an unpublished collaboration with Eugene Wigner.
  For Physics and Philosophy, a compilation of Margenau's articles on the philosophy of physics, Margenau was asked to write a brief autobiographical sketch to introduce the collection. It is filed under the book's title as a draft, and offers the most comprehensive biographical information of Margenau available in the collection, including his work as a consultant. Margenau also wrote a preface to the book, in which he describes the long and intimate relationship between physics and philosophy. The editor of the volume, Mario Bunge, also offers biographical information about Margenau, documenting his importance in both physics and philosophy. Bunge's biographical information can be found on the page directly before Margenau begins his autobiography.
  Of special note is the correspondence that followed in the wake of the publication of Ethics and Science. In a folder Margenau himself titled "reviews and controversy," there is an unfavorable review by philosopher Ernest Nagel. Margenau and Nagel carried on a dialogue in the pages of the New York Times regarding the role of scientists in matters of ethics and philosophy. Margenau also sent copies of the review and his reply to a number of friends and colleagues, and used what he considered the "controversy" as a starting point for at least two speeches he later delivered. Margenau's strong reaction to Nagel's opinion affords great insight into Margenau's personality, as well as into his views on the role of scientists, and others, in the fields of ethics and philosophy.
  Speeches, Lectures, Symposia (1950-1987) is comprised of writings Margenau prepared for public appearances. They document a wide-range of subject matter, though they are weighted heavily toward philosophical, ethical, and religious matters. Margenau was concerned that the sciences be integrated into society, and he felt that the teaching of physics was central to the cultural and ethical concerns of America. For example, in a 1953 speech, "Fusion or Fission: Can the Art of Living Together Prevail Over the Science of Destruction?" Margenau used common conceptions about scientific inquiry to compare communism, a dogma supported by ideology, to democracy, a way of life supported by facts. His aim was to demonstrate the power ideas may have over facts in certain circumstances. This is just one example of how Margenau saw his role as a scientist and a patriot merge with his role as an intellectual.
  Discussions (1934-1972) contains seven short published pieces on a variety of topics, and one typescript, accompanied by a letter from Eugene Wigner. The pieces were often collaborative, and fell under the rubric "discussion" or "news and views" in the publications in which they appeared. For the most part they are confined to clarifications of published articles, responses to criticism, and elaborations of theories or new ideas.
  The Other (n.d.) section contains writings that have not been identified for date or context. With the exception of "Annotated Writings of Others," however, they were all written by Margenau.
  - Publications by Henry Margenau, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Articles
    - Book Reviews, 1929-1980 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Philosophy, 1931-1981
      - "Advantages and Disadvantages of Various Interpretations of the Quantum Theory,", 1954 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - "An Approach to A Science of Psychical Research" [with Lawrence LeShan], 1980 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - "Are There Particles Traveling Faster Than Light?,", undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - "Atomic and Molecular Theory Since Bohr" (three parts)
        - "Historical Survey" [with Arthur Wightman], 1944 (Box 2, Folder 19)
        - "Logical and Mathematical Survey" [with Arthur Wightman], 1944 (Box 2, Folder 20)
        - Résumé of Specific Results [with R.B. Setlow], 1945 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - "Can Time Flow Backwards?,", 1954 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - "Causality,", 1960 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - "Causality and Modern Physics,", 1931 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - "Causality in Quantum Electrodynamics,", 1954 (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - "The Competence and Limitations of Scientific Method,", 1955 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - "Critical Points in Modern Physical Theory,", 1937 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - "Deductive Method in the Physical Sciences,", 1953 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - "Die Philosophie im xx. Jahrhundert" [German], 1959 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - "Effects of an Observer on Measurements in Quantum Mechanics,", undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - "Einstein's Conception of Reality,", 1949 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - "The Emergence of Integrative Concepts,", 1972 (Box 2, Folder 32)
      - "The Exclusion Principle and Its Philosophical Importance,", 1944 (Box 2, Folder 33)
      - "The Field Concept in Modern Science,", 1959 (Box 2, Folder 34)
      - "Fields,", undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
      - "Foundations of the Unity of Science,", 1941 (Box 2, Folder 36)
      - "Integrative Education in the Sciences,", 1967 (Box 2, Folder 37)
      - "Intercultural Communication of Ethical Judgments,", 1963 (Box 2, Folder 38)
      - "Knowledge, Faith and Physics,", 1954 (Box 2, Folder 39)
      - "The Meaning and the Faith of Science,", 1957 (Box 2, Folder 40)
      - "Meaning and Scientific Status of Causality,", 1934 (Box 2, Folder 41)
      - "Measurements and Quantum States" (2 parts), 1963 (Box 2, Folder 42)
      - "Measurement in Quantum Mechanics,", undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
      - "Measurements in Quantum Mechanics,", 1963 (Box 2, Folder 43)
      - "Metaphysical Elements in Physics,", 1941 (Box 2, Folder 45)
      - "The Method of Science: A Technical Summary,", 1945 (Box 2, Folder 46)
      - "Methodology of Modern Physics,", 1935 (Box 2, Folder 47)
      - "The Modern Predicament,", 1957 (Box 2, Folder 48)
      - "The Modern Predicament and Its Possible Removal,", 1957 (Box 2, Folder 49)
      - "Natural Science and Liberal Arts,", 1945 (Box 2, Folder 50)
      - "The New Style of Science,", 1963 (Box 2, Folder 51)
      - "On the Frequency Theory of Probability,", 1945 (Box 2, Folder 52)
      - "Perspectives of Science,", 1959 (Box 3, Folder 53)
      - "Phenomenology and Physics,", 1944 (Box 3, Folder 54)
      - "The Philosophical Legacy of Contemporary Quantum Theory,", 1966 (Box 3, Folder 55)
      - "Philosophical Perspectives of the Science of Modern Physics" [one page in English, the rest in Spanish], 1956 (Box 3, Folder 56)
      - "Philosophical Problems Concerning the Meaning of Measurement in Physics,", 1958 (Box 3, Folder 57)
      - "Philosophy of Physical Science in the Twentieth Century" [with J.E. Smith], 1958 (Box 3, Folder 58)
      - "Physics and Ontology,", 1952 (Box 3, Folder 59)
      - "Physics and the Doctrine of Reductionism,", 1981 (Box 3, Folder 60)
      - "A Principle of Resonance,", 1957 (Box 3, Folder 61)
      - "Probability and Causality in Modern Physics,", 1932 (Box 3, Folder 62)
      - "Probability, Many-Valued Logics, and Physics,", 1939 (Box 3, Folder 63)
      - "The Problem of Physical Explanation,", 1929 (Box 3, Folder 64)
      - "The Pursuit of Significance,", 1967 (Box 3, Folder 65)
      - "Quantum Mechanics, Free Will and Determinism,", 1967 (Box 3, Folder 66)
      - "Reality in Quantum Mechanics,", 1949 (Box 3, Folder 67)
      - "Relativity: An Epistemological Appraisal" [with Richard Mould], 1957 (Box 3, Folder 68)
      - "Report on the Recent Developments in the Philosophy of Quantum Mechanics" [with John Compton], 1950 (Box 3, Folder 69)
      - "Science and Ethics, Their Parallelism and some of its Consequences,", 1979 (Box 3, Folder 70)
      - "The Structure of the Philosophy of Science" [including a note from Margenau, 1990], undated (Box 3, Folder 71)
      - "The Teaching of Intermediate Physics,", 1938 (Box 3, Folder 72)
      - "Theory and Scientific Development,", undated (Box 3, Folder 73)
      - "Western Culture, Scientific Method and the Problem of Ethics,", 1947 (Box 3, Folder 74)
      - "Why Teach Philosophy of Science?,", 1957 (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Physics, 1927-1974
      - "Absorption Coefficient and Microwave Conductivity of Plasmas" [with P. Malozzi], 1963 (Box 4, Folder 76)
      - "Asymmetries of Pressure Broadened Spectral Lines,", 1933 (Box 4, Folder 77)
      - "Binding Energies of Light Nuclei,", 1939 (Box 4, Folder 78)
      - "Binding Energy of He6 and Nuclear Forces,", 1939 (Box 4, Folder 79)
      - "The Binding Energy of Li6" [with Kenneth G. Carroll], 1938 (Box 4, Folder 80)
      - "Collision Theories of Pressure Broadening of Spectral Lines" [with J.H. Van Vleck], 1949 (Box 4, Folder 81)
      - "Collisions of Alpha-Particles in Deuterium" [with E. Pollard], 1935 (Box 4, Folder 82)
      - "Collisions of Alpha-Particles in Hydrogen" [with E. Pollard], 1935 (Box 4, Folder 83)
      - "The Complex Neutron,", 1934 (Box 4, Folder 84)
      - "Conduction and Dispersion of Ionized Gases at High Frequencies,", 1946 (Box 4, Folder 85)
      - "Conductivity of Plasmas to Microwaves" [with Edward A. Desloge and Steven W. Matthysse], 1958 (Box 4, Folder 86)
      - "Correlation Between Measurements in Quantum Theory" [with Robert Nyden Hill], 1961 (Box 4, Folder 87)
      - "Dependence of Ultra-Violet Reflection of Silver on Plastic Deformation,", 1929 (Box 4, Folder 88)
      - "Effects of Electron Collisions on the Width of Spectral Lines" [with Bennett Kivel], 1955 (Box 4, Folder 89)
      - "Electron Conductivity and Mean Free Paths" [with Fred Adler], 1950 (Box 4, Folder 90)
      - "Electron Impact Broadening of Spectral Lines" [with B. Kivel and S. Bloom], 1954 (Box 4, Folder 91)
      - "The Equation State of Real Gases,", 1931 (Box 4, Folder 92)
      - "Excited States of the Alpha-Particle,", 1938 (Box 4, Folder 93)
      - "The Exclusion Principle and Measurement Theory,", 1966 (Box 4, Folder 94)
      - "Experimental Evidence Involving the Field of the Deuteron,", 1935 (Box 4, Folder 95)
      - "Fields in Physics and Biology: the Significance and Difficulties of Applied Field Theory,", 1959 (Box 4, Folder 96)
      - "Fields Within Fields Within Fields,", 1974 (Box 4, Folder 97)
      - "The Forces Between a Hydrogen Molecule and a Hydrogen Atom,", 1944 (Box 4, Folder 98)
      - "The Forces Between Hydrogen Molecules" [with Arthur A. Evett], 1953 (Box 4, Folder 99)
      - "Frequency Shifts in Hyperfine Splitting of Alkalis Caused by Foreign Gases" [with P. Fontana and L. Klein], 1959 (Box 4, Folder 100)
      - "A Correction,", 1961 (Box 4, Folder 101)
      - "Fysikkens Oprinnelse og Utvikling,", 1947 (Box 4, Folder 102)
      - "General Theory of Resonance Between Dipole Molecules" [with Dana T. Warren], 1937 (Box 4, Folder 103)
      - "High-Frequency Breakdown of Air" [with Donald Kelly], 1960 (Box 4, Folder 104)
      - "Interaction of Alpha-Particles,", 1941 (Box 4, Folder 105)
      - "Inversion Frequency of Ammonia and Molecular Interaction,", 1949 (Box 4, Folder 106)
      - "Ion Clustering" [with Stanley Bloom], 1952 (Box 4, Folder 107)
      - "Is the Mathematical Explanation of Physical Data Unique?,", 1960 (Box 4, Folder 108)
      - "Line Broadening by Electrons: Validity of Simple Theories" [with Ronald E. Meyerott], 1955 (Box 4, Folder 109)